我想问一下大家
I'd like to ask you,
以下这三个人有什么共同之处?
what do these three people have in common?
你们可能都认得第一位
Well, you probably recognize the first person.
我相信你们都是"美国偶像"的忠实观众
I'm sure you're all avid "American Idol" watchers.
你们也许不认识Aydah Al Jahani
But you might not recognize Aydah Al Jahani,
她是一位参赛选手 实际上
who is a contestant, indeed a finalist,
她是“百万诗人”比赛的决赛选手
in the Poet of the Millions competition,
这档节目不仅在阿卜杜比播出
which is broadcast out of Abu Dhabi,
在整个阿拉伯世界都有观众
and seen throughout the Arab world.
这个比赛
In this contest
要求选手创作并朗诵
people have to write and recite
原创诗歌 且为纳巴蒂体
original poetry, in the Nabati form of poetry,
这是一种传统的贝都因部落的诗歌形式
which is the traditional Bedouin form.
Lima Sahar也是一位决赛选手
And Lima Sahar was a finalist
她参加的是"阿富汗之星"歌唱比赛
in the Afghan Star singing competition.
在我继续之前
Now, before I go any further,
是的 我知道"英国达人"是此类节目的鼻祖
yes, I know it all began with "Britain's Got Talent."
但我所说的重点
But my point in discussing this
是想向大家说明-- 希望我可以讲清楚
is to show you -- I hope I'll be able to show you
这些比拼才艺的竞赛
how these merit-based competitions,
人人均可参与
with equal access to everyone,
通过短信投票选出胜者
with the winner selected via voting by SMS,
它们如何改变部落社会
are changing tribal societies.
我将以阿富汗
And I'm going to focus on Afghanistan
和阿拉伯世界的阿联酋为例
and the Arab world with the UAE,
他们改变部落社会的方法
how they're changing tribal societies,
并不是通过引入西方思想
not by introducing Western ideas,
而是通过融合各部落的语言
but by being integrated into the language in those places.
一切以娱乐开始
It all begins with enjoyment.
我们来不及看"阿富汗之星"了
Video: We are late to watch "Afghan Star."
我们要看"阿富汗之星" 已经晚了
We are going to watch "Afghan Star." We are late.
我们要晚了
We are running late.
我们一定要去看"阿富汗之星"
We must go to watch "Afghan Star."
这些节目已经深入人心
Cynthia Schneider: These programs are reaching incredibly deeply into society.
在阿富汗 人们不远数里
In Afghanistan, people go to extraordinary lengths
为了能够看到这个节目
to be able to watch this program.
自家没有电视也没有关系
And you don't necessarily have to have your own TV set.
全国上下都在收看这一节目
People watch it all over the country
甚至在公共场所都有得看
also in public places.
但不仅仅是观看这么简单
But it goes beyond watching,
因为 其中的一部分
because also, part of this
是拉选票
is campaigning.
人人参与
People become so engaged
甚至还有志愿者 类似政治选举的志愿者
that they have volunteers, just like political volunteers anyway,
他们跑遍全国上下
who fan out over the countryside,
为他们支持的选手拉票
campaigning for their candidate.
选手们也主动推销自己
Contestants also put themselves forward.
当然 一些人只把选票投给来自本地区的选手
Now, of course there is a certain degree of ethnic allegiance,
但并非完全如此
but not entirely.
因为每年的冠军都来自不同的部落
Because each year the winner has come from a different tribal group.
谁都可以报名参赛
This has opened up the door,
尤其是对于女性来说
particularly for women.
上一个赛季 有两位女选手闯入了决赛
And in the last season there were two women in the finalists.
其中一位的Lima Sahar是普什图族人 来自坎大哈
One of them, Lima Sahar, is a Pashtun from Kandahar,
一个非常保守的地区
a very conservative part of the country.
在"阿富汗之星"的记录片中 她告诉我们
And here she relates, in the documentary film "Afghan Star,"
她的朋友们劝她不要参赛
how her friends urged her not to do this
说她为了民主背离了他们
and told her that she was leaving them for democracy.
但同时她透露
But she also confides that
她知道有塔利班基地组织成员
she knows that members of the Taliban
发短信为她投票
are actually SMS-ing votes in for her.
Aydah Al Jahnani也是冒风险
Aydah Al Jahnani also took risks
去参加
and put herself out, to compete
“百万诗人”的比赛
in the Poet of the Millions competition.
我必须说 她的丈夫从一开始就支持她
I have to say, her husband backed her from the start.
但是她的部落和家庭都不支持
But her tribe and family urged her not to compete
甚至极力反对她参加
and were very much against it.
但当她开始赢得比赛时
But, once she started to win,
他们就开始支持她了
then they got behind her again.
看来竞争和好胜是全人类的价值取向
It turns out that competition and winning is a universal human value.
她参加比赛
And she's out there.
写的诗歌是关于女性
Her poetry is about women,
以及社会中妇女生活情况的
and the life of women in society.
仅仅通过展现自己
So just by presenting herself
和男性同台竞技
and being in competition with men --
从节目的投票结果可以看出
this shows the voting on the program --
她为年轻女性做出了很好的榜样
it sets a very important example for young women --
节目观众中有年轻女性
these are young women in the audience of the program --
在阿卜杜比 还有电视机前的观众
in Abu Dhabi, but also people in the viewing audience.
你们可能认为"美国偶像"
Now you'd think that "American Idol"
会带来美国化的潮流
would introduce a measure of Americanization.
但事实却恰恰相反
But actually, just the opposite is happening.
通过全民动员的形式
By using this engaging popular format
弘扬传统本土文化
for traditional, local culture,
实际上促使海湾地区人民
it actually, in the Gulf, is precipitating a revival
重拾对纳巴蒂体诗歌的关注
of interest in Nabati poetry,
传统服饰、舞蹈、音乐也开始得到复兴
also in traditional dress and dance and music.
在阿富汗
And for Afghanistan,
塔利班管制音乐已多年
where the Taliban banned music for many years,
这个活动重新向人们介绍了他们的传统音乐
it is reintroducing their traditional music.
他们不唱流行歌曲
They don't sing pop songs,
他们唱阿富汗民歌
they sing Afghan music.
他们也开始学会体面地接受失败
And they also have learned how to lose gracefully,
而不是对胜出者进行报复
without avenging the winner.
样样都很重要
No small thing.
最后 一种
And the final, sort of, formulation
终极版的“美国偶像”形式的节目
of this "American Idol" format,
在阿富汗新鲜出炉
which has just appeared in Afghanistan,
这档节目叫做“候选人”
is a new program called "The Candidate."
在节目中 人们提出
And in this program, people present
政策主张 然后进行投票
policy platforms that are then voted on.
虽然许多参赛选手太年轻 不能竞选总统
Many of them are too young to run for president,
但通过提出提议
but by putting the issues out there,
他们影响着总统竞选
they are influencing the presidential race.
对我来说 潜在的意义是
So for me, the substance of things unseen
看真人秀节目如何影响现实
is how reality TV is driving reality.
谢谢
Thank you.